Trees
surely among the
most magnificent of all living things
Some are the
largest organisms on Earth
dwarfing
all others
And these are the
tallest of them all
The deciduous and coniferous woodlands that grow in the seasonal parts of our planet
are the most
extensive forests on Earth
Their sheer
extent stuns the imagination
The barren
snows of the Arctic
A thousand miles
from the North Pole
And heading south
This is the very
first place the trees can grow
To begin with
the conifers are sparse
But soon
they dominate the land
This is the
tiger forest
There are as
many trees here
as in all the
world's rainforests combined
The tiger
circles the globe
and contains a
third of all the trees on Earth
It produces
so much oxygen
that it refreshes
the atmosphere of the entire planet
At the tiger's
northern extent
the growing season can last for just one month a year
It can take 50 years for a tree to get bigger than a seedling
It's a
silent world
where little stirs
But there are
occasional signs of life
stories
written in the snow
The prints of
an Arctic fox
and the hare it
might have been stalking
A female
polar bear
and her two cubs
Some animals are
so difficult to glimpse
that they're
like spirits
One could live a
lifetime in these woods
and never
see a lynx
The cat must roam
hundreds of miles in search of prey
And may never
visit the same patch of forest twice
It's the very
essence of wilderness
With so few
prey animals here
life for a hunter
is particularly hard
Creatures
are scarce
because few can
eat conifer needles
The moose is
an exception
Growth is
so difficult
that conifers
protect their precious leaves
by filling
them with resin
That reduces water loss
but it also makes
them very distasteful
At least the
conifer seeds are edible
But they're
protected within armourplated cones
And it takes a
specialist to reach them
The crossbill's
extraordinary beak
can prise
apart the scales
so that its
tongue can extract the seeds
Birds are
fortunate
When the seasonal
crop is gathered
they can fly south
But one animal is
so expert at survival in this frozen forest
that it stays
here and is active all year long
In local folklore
the wolverine is
a link to the spirit world
and a cross
between a bear and a wolf
In reality
it's a
huge weasel
Its bulk helps to
conserve body heat
and also
broadens its menu
It's so big
and powerful
it can even bring
down an adult caribou
For its size
it's said that the animal can eat more in one sitting than any other
which is why it's
also known as the glutton
Being
gluttonous here
is a very
effective strategy
It's wise to
eat all you can
when you can
And when even a
glutton can't eat more
It stores what'
s left for later
in the surrounding deep freeze
Spring in
the ice forest
The kapokayi can
also digest conifer needles
But feeding is
not its priority at the moment
Like gladiators
the males square
up for a battle
Each may have
just a single chance
to impress a female
Neither can
afford a lapse in concentration
The injured
loser may not survive
The inhabitants
of this great wilderness
May live and die
without ever
having contact with humanity
Long may it
be that way
The northern
forests may be the largest on earth
But to see coniferous trees that have reached their full potential
You must travel a
thousand miles south of here
The Pacific coast
of North America
The land
of hemlock
Douglas fir
and giant redwood
Here
water is never
locked up in ice
And even if
rains fail
the needles can
extract moisture from the fogs
That roll in
from the sea
The sun's energy
powers these forests
not for one month
as it does in the taiga
but for
half the year
These conifers grow at ten times the rate of those near the Arctic
And they live
for thousands of years
One grove of
redwoods in California
contains three of
the tallest trees on Earth
This one is over
a hundred metres high
the size of a 30-
storey building
These forests were growing here long before humans walked the earth
They were in
their prime 20 million years ago
And existed before the Swiss Alps or the Rocky Mountains
Were even raised
There is more living matter in a forest of giant conifers
than in any
tropical rainforest
But it's all
contained within the trees
These are as
inedible as those in the tiger
so animals
are still scarce
But they
are present
A pine martin
It's spring
The best
time of year
For a martin
to find food
Bird's eggs are
a seasonal snack
And for a
short time
there's
plenty of them
Sometimes
perhaps too many
But to live
here permanently
the martin needs
a more reliable food source
Squirrels
fit the bill
They thrive here
on the pine cones
And although
these are also seasonal
they can be stored and eaten throughout the year
The squirrels
are busy mating
Good news
for the hunter
A distracted squirrel
is a vulnerable squirrel
But this time
the amorous
couple are safe
There is a loner
stocking his larder
who will be
the easier target
Early summer
and great grey
owl chicks are fledging
Adults can only
raise young here
In years when the
seasonal vole crop is big enough to support them
The moment has
arrived for their first flight
Leapin' from the
world's tallest trees
is not for
the fainthearted
If you're
going to fall here
it's quite a good
idea to do it in stages
The ground is no
place for an owl
If he's to climb
to the top of his class
he'll need
to persevere
So now
let's have
another go
The American conifer forests may not be the richest in animal life
But their trees
are extraordinary
This giant sequoia
a relative
of the redwood
is the largest
living thing on earth
Known as
General Sherman
it's the weight
of ten blue whales
Higher up in the
nearby mountains
bristlecone pines
the oldest
organisms on the planet
Some have been
here for five thousand years
They were alive
before the pyramids were built
And were already
three thousand years old
When Christ was born
Across the equator
in the
southern hemisphere
There are forests
that mirror those of the north
Here in
South America
oricaria trees
or monkey puzzles
are like the
conifers of the tiger
They have waterproof scales instead of needles
and their cones
look a little different
but the
principles are the same
Slender billed parakeets rather than crossbills extract their seeds
Where the growing
season is longer
there are
alea trees
the redwoods
of the south
As in the
frozen north
the Valdivian
forests of Chile support very few animals
But that is the
end of the similarity
This is a bizarre
world of miniature creatures
The poodoo
the world's
smallest deer
feeds on the
giant leaves of the gunnera plant
The female is
just 30cm high at the shoulder
And her infants
are hardly bigger than kittens
The male
must stay alert
there are
hunters here
who would
snatch his young
Another miniature
the kodkod cat
It's the smallest
cat in all the Americas
And a young
poodle would be a feast for it
But with the
male on guard
the codcod must
lower his sights
Moths are hatching
they're the
last of the summer
The tiny cat
should be able to score with these
No one knows why
the creatures here are so small
But at least they
can survive on meagre rations
You might call
this a game of cat and moth
As winter
approaches in Chile
spring is arriving in the northern hemisphere
These are the
deciduous forests of home
Dormant
throughout the winter
they now undergo
one of the most
magical transformations
in the
natural world
By late spring
the landscape is
wrapped in a vibrant fresh green
Here
instead
of conifers
there are
broadleaf trees
And that makes the character of this forest entirely different
Being broad
these leaves
trap much more light than needles
But they'
re also thin
soft， and edible
And others can
eat the leaf eaters
It's spring
in the great
broadleaved forests
of Eastern Europe
and Asiatic Russia
The mandarin
ducks are courtin'
The female
mandarin nests in a tree hole
And when it's
time for everyone to leave
She leads the way
The ducklings are
only 24 hours old
It's a long drop
And a few calls
of encouragement are required
Two down
seven to go
There are
still two missing
All present
and correct
But they won't be
safe until they reach water
And the forest
pool is almost a mile away
By June
the days are
at their longest
And all across
the northern hemisphere
The broad leaves
are hard at work
On the east coast
of North America
it seems like
any other summer's evening
But tonight
is special
After 17
years underground
creatures
are stirring
The nymphs of the
periodical cicada
Have been
biding their time
Now they march
like zombies towards the nearest tree
And start to climb
At first
there are
merely thousands
But soon
more than a
billion swarm all over the forest
The biggest insect emergence on the planet is underway
They invade the
upper branches
Where they climb
out of their external skeletons
And assume their
adult winged form
At first
they're
white and soft
But they have until dawn to complete their transformation
After an
absence of 17 years
The forest is now
overrun by cicadas
The adults
are clumsy
and very edible
For turtles and
other inhabitants of the forest
This is a feast
they're lucky to see
Once in
their lifetime
And they gorge
themselves while they can
Times have
never been so good
The cicadas
have no defences
and virtually
offer themselves to their attackers
The stream of
insects is so relentless
That soon all the
predators are full to the point of bursting
And still the
cicadas come
With the
predators overwhelmed
the survivors can
achieve their purpose
After mating
the adults
lay their eggs
and then
their job is done
In just a few days
they will all die
and the forest
will fall silent
The cicadas here
will not be heard again
for another 17 years
Having fed
the predators
the cicadas
leave one final gift
for the
forest itself
The nutrients in
a generation of cicadas
are returned to
the soil all at once
And the trees
enjoy a marked spurt in growth
This may be the
single largest dose of fertilizer
in the
natural world
In the great
broadleaf forests of Eastern Europe
the days are
beginning to shorten
And a primeval
sound heralds the onset of autumn
Male red deer are
starting their rut
The air is heavy
with the scent of females
The rules
are simple
Winner takes all
Across the
northern hemisphere
the deciduous
forests are changing
Leaves that have
provided food and shelter since the spring
are now shed
In the broadleaf
forests of Russia
winter is
particularly severe
But there will
always be some
who benefit
from hardship
Black vultures
scavenge from the carcass
of a sika deer
that has died of cold or starvation
These endangered
birds are visitors
They've come
down from the north
to escape the
even colder conditions in Siberia
An Amur leopard
the rarest
cat on earth
Winter is a
difficult time for this hunter
There are no
leaves for cover
and no young
prey animals
This female has
the added pressure
of having to
provide for her oneyearold cub
It will be
another twelve months
before he'll be
able to fend for himself
The bickering
vultures have abandoned the carcass
It's a valuable
discovery for the leopards
But the cub doesn'
t share its mother's sense of urgency
The vultures have
left behind plenty of good meat
But it's
stiff with frost
The mother works
to open the hide
And make feeding
a little easier for her cub
There are only 40
Amur leopards left in the wild
And that number
is still falling
The harshness of
the winter here
hinders their
increase in numbers
It takes one of
these females longer
to raise her
young to independence
than it does a
leopard in Africa
If the mother can
sustain her cub for a few more weeks
spring will bring
an increase in prey
and her task
will lighten
For all the
inhabitants of this seasonal forest
the long cold
wait is nearly over
Spring in a
deciduous woodland is special
With no
leaves overhead
the rays of the
sun strike the forest floor directly
And their warmth
rouses plants from their winter sleep
The groundliving
plants are in a hurry
Before long the
trees above will come into leaf
and steal
their light
Their flowers
decorate the forest floor
As they advertise
their sweet nectar
To the newly
emerged insects
The spring blooms
of the deciduous woodlands
Have no equivalent in either the great conifer forests
Or the
tropical jungles
Within a
matter of weeks
the canopy
has closed
And only a few
wheeling shafts of light
Penetrate
the woodland
In the treetops
the broad leaves
rapidly expand to their full size
to make the most
of summer while it lasts
Then
after a
few months
the days begin
to shorten again
And the trees
must shut down and shed their leaves
In preparation
for the cold dark time ahead
Great tracts
of North America
flush red as the
season progresses
The effect is so
spectacular and so extensive
that it can be
seen from space
The threat of
winter frost
is not the only
reason for trees to shed leaves
These forests
stand in the tropics
Here
day length
never changes
But the dry
season is so severe
That the trees can
't afford to lose
The amount of
water that would evaporate
From their
broad leaves
So the leaves
must be shed
The forest resembles a European woodland in midwinter
But the heat
is overpowering
and its
inhabitants unfamiliar
For the creatures
of India's teak forests
these are
desperate times
But salvation is at hand
The marwa tree
is about to bloom
Its flowers are
full of liquid
making them
irresistible
The maawah is an
oasis in a hot dry desert
Those that
fly or climb
are not the only
ones to get a share
Chital deer
follow the langur monkeys
collecting the
flowers that fall
The monkeys
welcome the deer
for deer are
unrivalled at spotting predators
If they
are relaxed
it must be safe
to come down to the ground
and gather the
food that lies there
But it's not wise
to travel far from the sentinels
Tropical
Madagascar
The wet season
It's now that the
baobab trees regrow their leaves
and collect water
to store in their huge trunks
ready for the
dry season ahead
The prehistoric
shape of these trees is rightly famous
But few have ever
witnessed the baobab's real magic
For that
happens at night
and high in
the treetops
Flush with water
the baobab
prepares itself
for an unforgettable display
Once started
the footlong flowers can open fully in less than a minute
As the
flowers open
the creatures of
the forest wake
The mouse lemurs
have been hibernating throughout the dry season
With the
return of rains
it's time
to get busy
A dozen share
this tree hole
but there's
plenty of room
The world's
smallest primate
is no bigger
than your hand
High in the
branches above
the beehive's
nectar is starting to flow
A drink of
this sugary
energy
packed liquid
is an ideal way
for the lemurs
to start their day
Liquid oozes from
the flower's centre
and trickles
down the petals
But the nectar is
not intended for lemurs
These
giant hawkmoths
are the drinkers
the tree needs to attract
As they sip
moving from
tree to tree
So they
transfer pollen
and fertilise the flowers
Nectar was an
excellent first course for the lemurs
but moths are
the main dish
The moths are
very important to the lemurs
For they will
replenish the fat reserves
That the lemurs
need to survive the barren dry season
The lemurs might
seem to be a pest for the baobab
They kill its
pollinators and rob it of its nectar
But they do give
something in return
For as they
wrestle with the moths
their fur inevitably becomes dusted with pollen
So they too
become pollinators
As the alternation of wet and dry seasons brings change to some tropical forests
So the progression of summer to winter dictates life in more temperate regions
Whether trees
have needles or broad leaves
It is their
ability to survive annual change
That has
enabled them to cover
Such vast
areas of the earth
And made the
seasonal forests
The greatest
forests of all